AND FOR THIS AMAZING
>> [applause]
>> JUST AN AMAZING CONVERSATION. UM, like
you, um, Apostle Suleman, I sit at the
intersection of faith and education.
Minister in the church,
but also been a teacher, principal,
um, district leader. Done a lot of work
at the intersection of education and
faith while simultaneously holding the
faith. One of the things I want to go to
right away was this question or this
point that you made around fanaticism,
extremism.
Um, be- and you said it in a brilliant
way. You talked about the importance of
keeping one's faith,
but also hearing and being able to hear,
respect other individuals' faith. I
think one of the things that we're
struggling with particularly in this
country now is that extremist sort of
focus,
um,
or the belief and can I just say
sometimes it's with Christian people
in this country. The belief that if I
listen to others
and not project my sort of faith,
um, sort of dominant perspective, then I
in some ways am showing less of my
faith. Can you talk a little more about
that because you to you it was really
important to be in a position where I
can hear others, I can respect others, I
can
in some ways acknowledge and celebrate
others, but never feel like I have to
change who I am from a religious
perspective. Can you say a little more
about that?
>> Thank you very much. Very powerful and
and
intelligent question. Now,
um,
I think I think that, um, what is
extremism?
Extremism has to do
with
misunderstanding
um misunderstanding
your faith and the role that that faith
has to play. You see? And for
permit my bias as a Christian, when you
practice extremism in Christianity, you
are trying to take the place of God in
convicting the people.
You see that? Jesus who
um
Jesus who is the epicenter of the
Christian practice, in studying his
earth walk,
he related with people and he was silent
to listen to people as they communicated
their various perspectives.
Um whether it's John 4 with the woman,
the prostitute at the well, he sat with
tax collectors. He was not influenced by
them, but they were happy that he had an
open-hearted
um they were very frank conversations.
In fact, the scripture that represents
the core of the Christian faith, permit
me, John 3:16, came as a result of a
discourse
between an intelligent man and Jesus.
So, Nicodemus came to Jesus, the Bible
tells us, and he began to probe him
along the lines of, you know, why he was
here and so on and so forth. And you
would think that Jesus would turn and
say, "Get out of this place. You're one
of those people who offend me. Um you're
one of those nasty people." But he gave
him room to express himself and they
began to build a conversation. So, this
is my perspective. I do not believe, and
and this is my personal opinion, I do
not believe you have to fight, tear
down, insult um people to communicate
your faith. I do not think, in
particular, the Christian faith teaches
that. I do not believe that. And so, if
a Christian in this instance practices
that, I think the problem may be the
system of mentorship that the person has
submitted himself to.
Because, you see, permit me, Prof,
religion is like a gun. It depends on
who is holding it.
If a military man holds that gun, good
for the nation. If a terrorist holds the
same gun, bad for the nation. The gun
itself does not destroy. The gun assumes
the character of the one who holds it.
This is my concept, and this would be my
response to that.
>> Oh my goodness. OH MY GOODNESS.
>> [applause]
>> OKAY, I DIDN'T EXPECT TO HEAR RELIGION
LIKE A GUN TODAY, but that's powerful.
>> [laughter]
>> That's amazing. That's powerful. So,
what we've done in this country in some
ways, or just tell about us in light of
what you were saying about Africa, is
what we've said, because we can't trust
that people might go in that direction
of fanaticism, we will have no religion
talked about in the context of public
schools. Talk about the risk of that.
>> [sighs]
>> My lecture at the school of divinity
had a point of emphasis that from time
immemorial, Prof, all men, regardless
religious affiliations, have always had
a drive to connect to something,
to someone.
Now, my apologies, if you do not believe
in God, I respect your perspective, but
then I will tell you that all men crave
for connection.
To connect to their environment, to
connect sometimes with dimensions higher
than themselves. This has driven us, I
said in my speech, to test, try,
experiment
any and every available means that can
help feed that appetite for connection.
So, I respectfully disagree
with the philosophy that advocates
completely taking God out of a system.
This is my humble opinion, and with
every sense of respect and honor to the
laws of your land and your religious
orientation or otherwise. This is my
humble perspective. The reason is
because
in as much as we have all kinds of
limitations around the practice of
religion that includes Christianity,
Islam,
most religions in my personal study, and
believe me when I tell you I've studied
a number of world religions, you see,
I have found out that at the core of
their teachings, there is a straight
line that seems to unite these
perspectives. Albeit eventually people
diverge to various thoughts, but matters
of love,
matters of empathy, let's use that for a
case study. So, if even if it's to
preserve
faith practices on account of their
ability to promote love,
empathy,
unity, I think it is worth it. Now, when
a people are not governed by spiritual
convictions, the laws of the land will
only go so far.
That is the truth. That is the truth.
That is the truth. You see, so
I I I do not have the professional
capacity to probe into the factors that
may have led to formulating some of
these policies,
but then my humble my humble observation
and that will also be my suggestion is
that I am a firm believer that any
individual is not complete and whole
outside of your touch to spirituality
outside of your touch to your creator.
This is my humble observation.
>> I want to plant the seed powerful
statement there. I want to plant the
seed for the work of Professor at
Columbia University. Her name is Lisa
Miller.
And Lisa Miller is doing study on the
brain.
Doing imaging sort of study on the brain
and how the brain seems to be
sort of designed in a such a way that
spirituality is a core part of what it
seeks.
>> Absolutely.
>> Right? So she's actually trying to use
scientific study to show that
spirituality is actually critical in the
makeup how makeup of how the brain is
designed, which would confirm what
you're saying. One of the things you
talked a little bit about what you
hinted on it. I want to go a little
further into it and it was your personal
background.
Education.
Can you talk a little you talked about
colonialism and an indigenous. Talk a
little bit about how you were brought up
from an education standpoint, what that
experience looked like. Maybe I always
love asking this question. A favorite
teacher you had that actually impacted
you in a significant way so that we can
dive a little more in deeply into the
person someone.
>> Well, um
my grandfather
was one of the
the first trustees of a denomination
across northern Nigeria. So I come from
a lineage of missionaries.
And so that gave a very great leverage,
you know, born Christian home, you know,
lovely place. And then
I think that most of my educational
interactions have been around mission
schools and seminaries and this has
helped to shape my mindset. I give the
credit to
a man he's still alive. He's called
Archbishop Benjamin
And so he was a great influence in
helping to build the educational
community that trained us. You know, we
learned values like respect,
morals.
I remember you were prohibited from
taking licking taking candy or such and
then throwing it on the ground. He would
ask you to pick it up.
You know, and so on and so forth. So
those those were the earliest memories
of shaping my mind. I I also attended
an Air Force School and so but then
having these these religious
contributions, it it helped to shape my
understanding. I truly believe that part
of who and what I am today is also
credited to these formative years. The
opportunities that you know, came as a
result of that.
I do not know if I would still be the
Joshua Selman today
if I didn't pass through some of those
things. I truly believe that they
represent the anchors of my conviction
today. Yes, and so
I would I would I would just say the
teachers were wonderful people. We had
vigils, we had prayer,
we had all kinds of things. We had
activities that created bonding, mutual
respect. You know, we were taught
languages and several other things and I
feel that
when an individual has an opportunity to
pass through a system that is
faith-based, again my opinion, I believe
you are at a greater advantage. Truly, I
believe that. The difference became
clear when we looked at some of our
contemporaries who did not have the
privilege. Some of them had to with all
due respect, delve into drugs, delve
into so many things, you know, and some
of them up till now, some have lost
their lives, some have become inmates,
incarcerated in prison. And so, I think
that um that foundation of moral
excellence credited to faith-based um
um expressions in our lives have
contributed immensely to who I am today.
And I believe this is true for many
people.
>> Beautiful. My final question, and we'll
see if we have a question or so from the
audience. Um
when people ask me over the years why I
do what I do as a teacher, as a
principal, as a district leader, the
work that I've done,
one of the things that I say, and I
wonder if you would say the same, is I
feel like I'm called wow to do it. How
many people have used that word? I feel
a calling on my life.
>> Absolutely. Absolutely.
>> And that's often time we often respond
this way about secular work.
So, not necessarily about the preaching
that I do, but about the teaching or the
leading of schools. I feel a calling.
Answer this question if you would for
us. What does a calling mean to you? And
how how do you make sense of the fact
that you were called to do the spiritual
work while having an impact on the world
in many significant ways.
>> Very lovely question.
I don't see a call as a religious
statement.
Um I understand a call to mean your
contribution to your world.
When you discover yourself,
when you discover your giftings, when
you refine yourself,
responding to your call
is bringing honor to yourself by
allowing that which is within you to be
released to your world to make it a
better place. So, for me, your call is
your contribution
to making your world and your
environment a better place. And it
doesn't have to be from a religious
fanatical So, I consider a preacher, and
a lecturer, a chef, and an
administrator, if their motivation is to
be a blessing, I consider that them
called.
>> [applause]
>> Now, I would say this, Prof. I would say
this. Um I was greatly mentored by the
late Dr. Myles Munroe.
>> Yes.
Myles Munroe.
>> [applause]
>> Now,
Dr. Myles Munroe was an incredible
person. Um
when I was beginning, you know, this
work, I wrote a letter to so many
people, you know, just asking their
perspectives. It was Dr. Myles Munroe
who replied me back handwritten.
>> Wow.
>> He encouraged me and let me know that I
could become anything.
I loved him because he approached faith
and nation-building from an intelligent,
non-
fanatical, non-extremist standpoint. He
had the largest church then in Bahamas,
and yet he was adviser to many
presidents. Did you know, I hope my
history is still right, that when
Nelson Mandela was about to be released,
he and one other were the people who
were delegated to go and receive him.
So, these are people whose impact moves
from faith, but beyond the walls
of religion.
>> [applause]
>> Absolutely.
>> So, with
with that backdrop, I made up my mind
that I wanted to be an individual, not
just known for spirituality,
but from the springboard, the standpoint
of spirituality, that I'm able to spread
my influence to affect all and sundry,
regardless your faith orientation,
regardless your religious affiliation, I
believe that I have a contribution to
make to your life. And if I propose to
you what is behind my convictions, and
even if you reject it, it is still not
enough reason to not impact you. There
is always something you can learn. By
the way, Selman means the way to love.
You will want to know that.
>> [applause]
>> One last thing before we end on this
calling point point. Just so it sinks in
with everybody. Everyone turn and find
someone, look them dead in the eye, turn
and look at somebody, look at someone,
and ask them this question, "Do you know
your calling?"
>> [laughter]
>> Let's give Let's give Apostle Selman a
round of applause real quick.
>> [applause]
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you again so much, and the panels
can still remain here.
This was such a phenomenal event. Um
Apostle Selman, I hope this is not the
last time that you'll be coming to
Harvard. Can we get that on record? Will
you be coming back again?
>> I hope, I pray,
>> [laughter]
>> I think.
>> So, it's it's on the record that he'll
be coming back, okay? Because we we did
not have nearly enough time with you
here at the Graduate School of
Education. I think that other parts of
the university would want to engage with
you. And the note that he ended on with,
too, I just want to
That blesses me so much. So, Dr. Myles
Munroe was my pastor in the Bahamas and
my mom's pastor. And so,
>> [applause]
>> as a kid, every Saturday I would sell
fruits with my mom to him and his wife,
Ruth Ann.
Every he wrote my letter of
recommendation for college to come to
the United States. And you know, to
think about the impact that he's had on
your life and now you're coming back
here. And and it's so powerful because
when we think about the mission of the
Harvard Graduate School of Education,
it's about preparing
leaders and innovators in education to
provide opportunities for learners from
all around the world. And that story is
so interconnected, right? It's
connecting the Bahamas with Nigeria with
the United States of America, too. And
so this is this is such an incredible
incredible moment. I want before we
leave, we have a gift to give you on
behalf of the Harvard Graduate School of
Education. And I want to invite a couple
of folks here to be um a part of this
presentation. Uh Ruth Okediji is one of
our faculty members. Um Dele Ogunseitan,
my mom from the Bahamas. And then Marty
West, please come up, Marty, our
academic dean.
>> [applause]
>> Yeah, please please please come down.
And feel free to take pictures, too. Um
we we believe that that in the in the
scriptures it says your gift will make
room for you. And whenever you come into
the presence of someone with greatness,
you want to come bearing gifts. Um when
the when folks came to Jesus's birth,
they came bearing gifts. And so we have
we have awesome swag here at the Harvard
Graduate School of Education.
>> [laughter]
>> So there's there's a Moleskine in here
so that you can write your notes on this
Harvard ledger. There's a nice water
bottle, you know, so that there's living
water coming out of you. So we're going
to put some some actual water in you.
And then we we we we got a we got a bag
in here, too. So this is this is for
your blessing. So when people come and
give into your bag, there's something
that they can receive, too. So again,
thank you so much for coming to Harvard.
I just wanted to give you an opportunity
to say something.
>> Uh you're Peter, you're a tough act to
follow. Uh
>> [laughter]
>> so
Apostle Solomon, it's a delight to have
you here. What Peter said about our
mission really captures what it is we're
trying to do at the Harvard Graduate
School of Education and would welcome
any opportunity to partner with you
going forward. So, thank you.
>> And and Ruth, you're not going to
escape.
This is this is my spiritual mama here.
Come here. Mhm. You're not going to
escape. You got to say a little
something.
>> Um thank you all for being here. I want
to thank um Marty who is just um we
don't see each other enough, but we know
we're here and I know that um he thinks
and prays about this institution and
about other colleagues and certainly
about the School of Education. And I
said to both um Dr. Scott and and uh
Professor Blair that
for those of you who are Harvard
students and Harvard faculty, you rarely
see the School of Education in the
Crimson or the Gazette or the New York
Times,
but when we think of what knowledge does
to open the way for faith, for the
improvement of humanity, for
contributions to society, this is the
crown jewel of Harvard University. And
I'm so grateful for Marty's leadership,
for all of you, for the work that is
happening here because education not
only opens doors, but it is a leveler.
It's the thing that people will look at
and say, "God has given you a gift. You
can go out and be whoever you want to
be." Every teacher has been such a
blessing in my life. My parents were
teachers, and so I'm incredible
incredibly grateful to the Harvard
School of Graduate Education. Thank you.
>> [applause]
>> All right.
And
just one other thing. I'm known for my
selfies. I need to get you folks into a
selfie.
And then after that, we We a very
delicious um
>> reception please. Would you permit me so
he can do the speech?
>> Oh, sure. Okay, sure. Yeah.
And we have a very we have a very
delicious spread, um, outside of of
wonderful refreshments.
>> Come on, you guys take a picture so
people can eat.
>> Are we done?
>> Yeah.
>> Awesome, awesome. Well, thank you so
much. Enjoy the food outside as you exit
it's going to be on your left here. We
have a really nice spread. And if you've
come in from out of town to Harvard,
please, um, traverse the campus and see
all that we have to offer here. Welcome.